Welcome back to a push in under three
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. So, the Civil War is over. So
many battles of attrition along with
various scorched earth policies have
caused the South to be in ruins,
literally. Yes, the South had lost the
war, but now they were a part of the
Union again. So, the government tried to
usher in an era known as reconstruction
to rebuild the South. Originally during
the war, Lincoln issued his 10% plan
that told the South he would readmit a
southern state to the Union and give it
America's protection and benefit so long
as 10% of the voters pledge loyalty to
him. Lincoln's plan aimed to be lenient
and avoid punishing the South, focusing
on restoring the Union quickly. But then
Lincoln had to go and die in 1865 by
John Wils Booth, which upset quite a
bit. Andrew Johnson came in and gave his
plan, which was very similar to Lincoln,
apart from offering pardons to former
Confederates. Then later in
reconstruction, the radical Republican
plan was put into effect as Republicans
gained more power. This was meant to
punish the South, protect black rights,
and send the military to enforce it. The
South absolutely hated this. And the
thing is, Andrew Johnson hated radical
Republicans and tried to veto
everything. Congress responded by
impeaching him, making him the first US
president to almost be removed from
office. Reconstruction also allowed some
amendments to be passed as well. the
13th amendment which abolished slavery,
the 14th, which granted birthright
citizenship and equal protection under
the law, and the 15th, which gave black
men the right to vote. But even though
this seems like a good idea, you need to
understand that this era was really no
better for African-Americans than before
the Civil War. Almost immediately after
the southern states were readmitted to
the Union, they passed black codes,
which were codes in the South that
limited freedoms of African-Americans
and continuously forced
African-Americans into forced labor.
Despite slavery being technically over,
blacks worked the fields in a system
known as sharecropping where it wasn't
technically slave labor, but with their
wages, it might as well have been. There
would be public events held in the South
where people would gather to watch
African-Americans be hanged or tred and
feathered or any number of ways to die
known as lynchings. And then you have
organizations like the Ku Klux Clan and
the White League, which used literal
terrorism to suppress black voters. All
of this would force the North to just
give up entirely and cause
reconstruction to fail. But that is the
next video problem. On the screen now
are some AP style questions for this
topic. Pause
now. I'll put the answers on the screen
now. I will see you in the next one.